<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic Service | Hello, World!</title>
    <link>http://himelmallick.github.io/tags/academic-service/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://himelmallick.github.io/tags/academic-service/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Academic Service</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://himelmallick.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Academic Service</title>
      <link>http://himelmallick.github.io/tags/academic-service/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yearender: Looking back at 2021</title>
      <link>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/yearender_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/yearender_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every year a set of memes is circulated widely on social media, the 2022 version of which goes along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;My goal for 2022 is to accomplish the goals of 2021 which I should have done in 2020 because I made a promise in 2019 and planned in 2018.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, this remained my most favorite ‘new year’ meme for no real reason other than that it was hilarious, funny, and relatable, but in 2021, the actuality of these lines hit me hard as it tested my mettle out and out by bestowing a series of unfinished businesses and frequent hiccups throughout the year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timeline of this blog post spans approximately two pandemic years (2020-2021) as it dates back to my planned month-long India trip when the COVID-19 situation in India was better than what it was in the US (Fall, 2020). A chain of abrupt COVID cancellations later, my much-awaited India trip finally materialized in April 2021 - little did I know that my spring sojourn was on the verge of becoming a lengthy nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks into my arrival, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timeline_of_the_COVID-19_pandemic_in_April_2021&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a second wave of the  global disease outbreak&lt;/a&gt; wreaked havoc across the nation. With a nearly collapsed health care system, India&amp;rsquo;s pandemic suddenly turned into a human tragedy in quick succession. As the difficult days unfolded, it was just a matter of time that the COVID-19 pandemic disrupted the normal living, and I was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unprecedented consequences of the pandemic have been widely reported in the media but there are a few things that personally affected me more than anything, which broadly manifested as a general decrease in productivity at the expense of regular mental and emotional breakdowns, including but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insurmountable personal losses&lt;/strong&gt; (It&amp;rsquo;s one thing to read the news or track the worldometer, but it&amp;rsquo;s a whole different ballgame to witness personal losses up close and personal and hear individual stories that are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/world/india/situation-india-beyond-heartbreaking-who-chief-says-2021-04-26/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;beyond heartbreaking&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delayed academic collaborations&lt;/strong&gt; (As much as I wanted to keep the &lt;a href=&#34;http://himelmallick.github.io/post/year_end_reflection_2020/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2020 momentum&lt;/a&gt; going, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00663-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pandemic burnout&lt;/a&gt; turned out to be real, which slowly but surely led to an inevitable slowdown in productiveness.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID diagnosis with moderate-to-severe symptoms&lt;/strong&gt; (A massive turning point was testing postive for COVID-19 with fairly severe symptoms. Although I was fortunate to escape a visit to the hospital (thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Favipiravir&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Favipiravir&lt;/a&gt;), the experience of end-to-end recovery was gruesome.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immigration uncertainty and travel ban&lt;/strong&gt; (An icing on the cake was immigration uncertainty induced by closures of consulates and embassies and the subsequent travel ban (not to forget the curfews and lockdown measures from time to time). I mean nothing more painful than having a confirmed interview appointment, and then finding out that it was cancelled only after traveling 1000 miles. All in all, it took 5 months, several round-trip flights, and multiple letters and email exchanges to finally secure a VISA interview in the capital.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aftermath of Hurricane Ida&lt;/strong&gt; (The final nail in the coffin came in the form of Hurricane Ida when I was able to finally return to the US in September 2021. In case you are wondering, life without a car in New Jersey is not as manageable as in other states, which is precisely why the experience of becoming a victim of a flooded out car (declared total loss by insurance) is not a great one. This was further exacerbated by an expired driver&amp;rsquo;s license and &lt;a href=&#34;https://nj1015.com/car-shopping-in-nj-right-now-is-a-nightmare-my-story-and-some-advice-opinion/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortage of new cars in the area&lt;/a&gt;, adding to the worry and already-mounting anxiety).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I come in terms with a particularly difficult year and reflect, there are a number of positive things that I am grateful for, which in turn made the journey a lot more easier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A long overdue family reunion and precious quality time with the extended family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completion of a six-month-long &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ccl.org/leadership-programs/leadership-development-program/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;leadership course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;gt;10K &lt;a href=&#34;http://bioconductor.org/packages/stats/bioc/Maaslin2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;official downloads&lt;/a&gt; of our software tool (&lt;a href=&#34;https://huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/maaslin/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MaAsLin 2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;gt;100 &lt;a href=&#34;https://publons.com/researcher/1190507/himel-mallick/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publons-verified reviews&lt;/a&gt; and &amp;gt;2500 &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=twbXG-wAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Scholar citations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Back-to-back keynote presentations including an extremely fulfilling &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YV_KRtMfqr0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;BVCN featured talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promotion to Associate Principal Scientist at work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum it up, instead of dwelling on the negatives, I made a solemn pledge this year to embrace things that didn&amp;rsquo;t go well in 2021, which in retrospect, was precisely what I needed to press that reset button and start the new year on a high note! Welcome, 2022!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Featured image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.istockphoto.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.istockphoto.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Year-end reflection: My 2020 highlights</title>
      <link>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/year_end_reflection_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/year_end_reflection_2020/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The last day of 2020 is finally here. To bring this decade to a close, I thought I would take a moment to share some of the highlights from this year in the form of pictures and anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as I would love to remember this year as a year of &lt;code&gt;setbacks and bottlenecks&lt;/code&gt;, in retrospect, it has been packed with some very surprising yet noteworthy moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal level, 2020 has been a year of many firsts, much as has been the case for the society in general where we have together achieved incredible things as a community despite challenging circumstances. From delivering vaccines in record time to abiding by the social distancing guidelines to adjusting to the &lt;code&gt;new normal&lt;/code&gt;, we have come a stunningly long way in a short period of time, which I believe, prepares us well for a pandemic-proof future in 2021 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some things that went surprisingly well during the entire thriving process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-year-resolutions&#34;&gt;New year resolutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my new year resolutions in 2020 was to write at least one piece of writing every month (technical or non-technical). This seemed like a lofty goal at the outset but I am glad that I was able to break this seemingly hard-to-attain goal into manageable chunks to make it a reality. In my mind, this was a monumental personal milestone as it allowed me to build a decent writing habit which has been difficult historically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;10000-steps-per-day&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;10000 steps per day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another seemingly unattainable habit (based on past experiences) was consistently hitting an average &amp;gt;10,000 steps a day for an extended period of time (i.e. more than a few weeks or months), which I was able to achieve despite the almost year round lockdown. Considering all the obstacles that stood in the way this year, it was a truly transformative experience to start 2021 on a &lt;code&gt;lighter&lt;/code&gt; note!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-back-into-creative-writing&#34;&gt;Getting back into creative writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the year, I was fortunate to enroll in a &lt;code&gt;screenwriting&lt;/code&gt; class. Among other things, this was my best chance at getting back into creative writing. As a result of this experience, I was able to write a few short scripts in addition to a few amateur poems which was enough to eventually claw my way to get my writer’s groove back :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-commit-record&#34;&gt;Personal commit record&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, almost accidentally, I broke my own record of GitHub commits, which was more than all the previous years combined. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more happy about this &lt;code&gt;unexpected&lt;/code&gt; milestone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-peer-review-record&#34;&gt;Personal peer-review record&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the same token, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more appreciative of the opportunity to give back to the scientific community through voluntary contributions in the form of peer-review activities. Consequently, I was able to break my own record of &lt;a href=&#34;https://publons.com/researcher/1190507/himel-mallick/metrics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Publons-verified peer-reviews&lt;/a&gt;, which was again &lt;code&gt;accidentally&lt;/code&gt; more than all previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from these, there have been a few &lt;code&gt;first-of-its-kind&lt;/code&gt; professional highlights this year as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed my first internship as a mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edited my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://himelmallick.github.io/post/guest_editing_reflection/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;special issue&lt;/a&gt; as a lead editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Published my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/Maaslin2.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bioconductor package&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivered my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Mallick_Himel/status/1260271590320885764&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;keynote presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organized my first &lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.amstat.org/meetings/jsm/2021/invitedsessions.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;JSM invited session&lt;/a&gt; (scheduled for JSM 2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that note, I would love to hear your highlights from the year, so be sure to leave a comment :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wishing you and yours a safe, healthy, and prosperous new year! Onwards and upwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Featured image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.the-scientist.com/news-opinion/what-to-expect-in-the-publishing-world-in-2020--66882&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.the-scientist.com/news-opinion/what-to-expect-in-the-publishing-world-in-2020&amp;ndash;66882&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A reflection on my first guest editorial experience</title>
      <link>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/guest_editing_reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://himelmallick.github.io/post/guest_editing_reflection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had a chance to wrap up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/8604/statistical-and-computational-methods-for-microbiome-multi-omics-data&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;special issue&lt;/a&gt; at the journal &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Frontiers in Genetics&lt;/a&gt;. This is my first-hand experience as a lead Guest Associate Editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, this opportunity came to me at a time when I was exponentially busy as a postdoctoral fellow juggling research, occasional teaching and other administrative duties while also preparing my transition to a new role. I am so glad I took the chance when the Frontiers editorial office reached out to me in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of (i) proposing a research topic, (ii) putting together a team of co-editors, (iii) reaching out to potential contributors, (iv) handling manuscripts on a shared basis, (v) assigning reviewers, (vi) collectively deciding the fate of the manuscripts often over multiple rounds, and (vii) finally closing the special issue with an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fgene.2020.00927/full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; - it has been a long and fulfilling journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 11 articles in this research topic including an editorial, where we have curated high-quality articles published between April 2019 and July 2020 on various topics in microbiome and multi-omics data science (snapshotted below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Image_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;image info&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the papers have already been highly shared over the last year or so and they have together generated &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/8604/statistical-and-computational-methods-for-microbiome-multi-omics-data#impact&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;60K&lt;/a&gt; views within a short amount of time. Many thanks to all the authors and editorial contributors for your support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/13026/methods-for-single-cell-and-microbiome-sequencing-data&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;second round&lt;/a&gt; of this Research Topic which is currently open for new research, methodology, review, and comment articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you all have a chance to catch up on some of the progress made in the field :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
